<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short catechisme, summarily comprizing the principall points of Christian faith, somewhat corrected and augmented by Iames Balmford Minister</title>
            <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114854</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850077</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 871:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short catechisme, summarily comprizing the principall points of Christian faith, somewhat corrected and augmented by Iames Balmford Minister</title>
                  <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Richard Boyle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A necessarie catechisme for all Christians.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15261:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SHORT CATE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHISME, SVMMARI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY COMPRIZING THE Principall points of Chriſtian faith, <hi>ſomewhat corrected and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by</hi> IAMES BALMFORD <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prou. 24. 27.</bibl> Prepare thy worke without, and make ready thy things in the field, and after build thine houſe.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for RICHARD BOYLE. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15261:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15261:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, THE Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> Wardens, Aſsistants, and whole <hi>company of Carpenters in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, IAMES BALMFORD, a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters</hi> ſonne, and a builder, according to his calling and gifts, wiſheth the continuall edification of their godly faith while they trauaile in this vale of teares, and at the last the end of that faith euen the ſaluation of their Soules.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His litle Catechiſme hath been long in Print, but not yet dedicated vnto any. Being now to reprint it with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther litle treatiſes, I haue thought it conuenient to dedicate it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, as a monument of my thankefulnes for your many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, but eſpecially for your
<pb facs="tcp:15261:3"/> charitable exhibition, when I was a poore ſtudent in <hi>Oxford;</hi> Hoping that this dedication wil not only incourage you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, and increaſe (as God ſhall inable) your Chriſtian chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to Students of good hope in either Vniuerſitie (than which I know not a more charitable, and fruitfull worke of faith) but alſo ſtirre you vp both to reade the Catechiſme diligently your ſelues, &amp; carefully to cauſe your families to learne it. For it is commonly ſeene; that (howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer too many be newfangled, yet for the moſt part) men are rather moued with thoſe Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which are expreſſely &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially addreſſed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and that by ſuch as, in ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſort, belong vnto them. This only I deſire, that ye would take ſome paines in examining the
<pb facs="tcp:15261:3"/> quotations, becauſe they giue both light vnto the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and warrant to the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſeuerall points of this Catechiſme.</p>
            <p>I doubt not of your good wil; but whereas this Catechiſme is likely to come into the hands of ſome, who will not, with you, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine it fauourablie for my ſake, I ſuppoſe this obiection: One generall, and well concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Catechiſme doth moſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; therefore many are but to litle purpoſe: Whereunto I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and freely anſwere; That, hauing experience how profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the ſtudies of children haue been furthered, ſince diuerſitie of Grammars hath been aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and one certaine Grammar generally to be taught, by act of Parliament eſtabliſhed, I grant that one generall and well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb facs="tcp:15261:4"/> Catechiſme doth moſt edifie, in reſpect of publike vſe: But I am aſſured, that, as ſundry Grammars, ſo ſundry Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes doe much good in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ſtudie, and vſe. For the ſame method of teaching which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſome plauſible &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, plaine and profitable, doth not ſeeme ſo to other; And one Catechiſme doth more cleerely lay ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome points of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith, than another, yea handleth ſome neceſſary point, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other doth altogether omit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, It helpeth much to the confirmation of faith, when it is ſeene, that, howſoeuer ſundry men in ſundry ages &amp; countries, publiſh ſundry Catechiſmes, or make ſundry confeſſions (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene which two there is no great difference) as to ſay with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, Behold the Lambe of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 29.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:15261:4"/> 
               <hi>God which taketh away the ſins of the world;</hi> or with <hi>Peter, Thou art the Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God,</hi> the one publiſhing his office, the other confeſſing his nature; yet they hold the ſame <hi>Head,</hi> belieue in the ſame <hi>Chriſt,</hi> iuſtifie the ſame <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> and profeſſe the ſame <hi>Truth.</hi> What great profit do Gods children reape by the <hi>Harmony of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſsions,</hi> as of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſo of ancient and late wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? What benefit hath, and doth redound to the Church of God by ſundry <hi>Creeds,</hi> not only extant, but ſome of them in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique vſe too, as the <hi>Apoſtolique, Nicene,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian,</hi> euery one doth know, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. In theſe conſiderations I conceiue hope, that this litle Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme will bee offenſiue to none, but acceptable to you, and profitable to all ſuch, as with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb facs="tcp:15261:5"/> humilitie will vſe, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe it. And the rather, becauſe they ſhall find the moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doctrine of the Lords Supper more plainely ſet downe in this Catechiſme, than in many other of no greater volume.</p>
            <p>Well, what good opinion ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer this Catechiſme ſhall find in the hearts of other Readers, let me exhort you as a brother, to edifie your ſelues, with all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diligence, eſpecially in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Word</hi> preached, and (as you may) in reading firſt the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and then other <hi>Godly</hi> Treatiſes; Vnderſtanding that <hi>Edification,</hi> ſo much comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and commanded in <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> doth ſignify <hi>Building.</hi> Of which ſpirituall building, your tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall building ſhould daylie put you in mind; Leſt otherwiſe yee incurre a cenſure and ſentence,
<pb facs="tcp:15261:5"/> like to that of the Prophet <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 1. 4. 6. 1. Cor. 3. 9. 16.</note> viz. <hi>Can yee build houſes for your ſelues, and other; and will yee careleſſely ſuffer the Temple of the Lord (which is your ſelues) to lie waſte? Yee ſhall therefore earne wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and put them into a broken bag.</hi> But hoping (as I wiſh) that yee will more and more apply your hearts vnto wiſedome, euen that wiſedome which is vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I commend you to <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Word</hi> of his grace, which is able to build further, and to giue you an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:15261:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15261:6"/>
            <head>A ſhort Catechiſme, <hi>neceſſarie to be learned of</hi> all Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>. WHo is the Creator and gouernour of this world?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="a" place="margin">Geneſ. 1. Eſay 45. 5.</note> One God, in whom there bee thrée perſons, <note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>John 5. 7.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Of all viſible creatures which is the chiefeſt?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="c" place="margin">Geneſ. 1. 26. Pſal. 8. 5.</note> Man.</p>
            <p>Q. After what manner made hee him?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="d" place="margin">Geneſ. 1. 26.</note> Like vnto himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Q. How was that?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="e" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 31. Epheſ. 4. 24.</note> Frée from ſinne, and perfect in righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>Q. To what end made hee him righteous?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 73. Eſay 43. 7.</note> To ſerue him.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15261:7"/>
            <p>Q. Did man continue righteous?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="g" place="margin">Geneſ. 3. 6. 7. 10.</note> No: he ſell from righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to ſinne.</p>
            <p>Q. How did he fall into ſinne?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="h" place="margin">Geneſ. 3 6. 7.</note> By cating the forbidden fruit.</p>
            <p>Q. What abilitie was left in man to ſerue God after that ſinne?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="i" place="margin">Geneſ. 6. 5. Ierem. 4. 22. Epheſ. 4. 18.</note> None at all, either in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or affection.</p>
            <p>Q. Did that ſinne reſt in <hi>Adam</hi> alone?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="k" place="margin">Iohn 3. 6. Rom. 5. 12.</note> No: it deſcendeth from him into all mankind.</p>
            <p>Q. What fruites doth it bring forth in all mankind?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="l" place="margin">Geneſ. 6. 5. Rom. 5. 12. &amp;c.</note> Sinfull thoughts, words, and déeds.</p>
            <p>Q. What is the puniſhment due for ſinne?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="m" place="margin">Geneſ. 2. 17. Rom. 6. 12. &amp; 6. 23.</note> Euerlaſting death and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Q. How come we to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 3. 20.</note> By the Law.</p>
            <p>Q. Wherunto ſerueth this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 2. 37. &amp; 24. 26. 1. Cor. 14. 24. 25.</note> To humble man, and to caſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15261:7"/> him downe in the conſideration of his owne miſerie.</p>
            <p>Q. How is it poſſible for man to be ſaued in this miſerie?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="p" place="margin">Matth. 1. 21. &amp; 11. 28. Act. 4. 12. &amp; 10. 43.</note> By Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. What is Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 9. 5. Matth. 1. 23.</note> God and <note n="r" place="margin">Eſay 9. 6.</note> Man in <note n="ſ" place="margin">Gal. 4. 4.</note> one perſon.</p>
            <p>Q. Wherefore was he man?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 4. 4. 5. Heb. 2. 9. 10. 11</note> To do thoſe things which were to be done for mans redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Q. What be they?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="u" place="margin">Philip. 2. 7. 8. 9. 10.</note> His ſuffering, <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 5 17.</note> righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <note n="*" place="margin">&amp; 16. 28.</note> and triumphing.</p>
            <p>Q. Wherefore was he God alſo?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="x" place="margin">Hebr. 9. 14. Coloſ. 2. 9. &amp;c.</note> That the doings of his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood might be of infinite vertue.</p>
            <p>Q. Why did Chriſt ſuffer death?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 3. 24. 25.</note> To be our <hi>Iustification.</hi> In acquiting <note n="z" place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 13. 14. 15.</note> vs of our ſinne, <note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. 1. 18. 19.</hi>
               </note> by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging the puniſhment due there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>Q. Why was Chriſt righteous?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Cer. 1. 30. 31.</hi>
               </note> To be our <hi>Sanctification,</hi> in making <note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 17. 19.</note> vs holy in ſome meaſure, <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 28. 38.</note> and to couer the imperfection of our holines.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15261:8"/>
            <p>Q. What benefit inſueth that <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification</hi> which we haue by Chriſt?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 1. 16. 17. &amp; 6. 13.</note> Euerlaſting life which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> loſt by ſinne.</p>
            <p>Q. What be the doings of Chriſt his triumph?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 15. 55. 57.</hi>
               </note> Reſurrection from death, and <note n="f" place="margin">Epheſ 4. 8.</note> Aſcention into heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. Why did he ariſe from death?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 4. 25. &amp; 8. 34.</note> To ſeale the merits of his ſufferings for our <hi>Iustification,</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 15. 57.</hi>
               </note> and to ouercome death for vs.</p>
            <p>Q. Why did he aſcend into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 8. 34.</note> To make continuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to procure <note n="k" place="margin">Hebr. 7. 25.</note> ſauing helpe, and to <note n="l" place="margin">Iohn 14. 1. 2.</note> take poſſeſſion for vs.</p>
            <p>Q. How are we made partakers of theſe foure meritorious workes of Chriſt, to wit, his <hi>Death, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>Aſcention?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 3. 16. Philip. 3. 9. 10.</note> By a true Faith.</p>
            <p>Q. What is Faith?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="n" place="margin">Hebr. 10. 22. 11. 1. 1. Tim. 1. 15. 16.</note> A full perſwaſion that God is merciful to me for his Son Chriſt his ſake.</p>
            <p>Q. If a true faith bee ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15261:8"/> who then bee partakers of thoſe foure meritorious workes of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>A. True faith is alwaies ſuch in it owne nature, but beleeuers are not alwaies ſenſible of ſo great a comfort, becauſe of their infirmities.</p>
            <p>Q. May I craue ſome proofe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for my confirmation, &amp; comfort?</p>
            <p>A. Conſider well, 1. The quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted proofes of the deſcription of <hi>Faith.</hi> 2. That otherwiſe it ſhould not differ, either fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Opinion</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Luke 24. 21. 25. Act. 26. 28. 29.</note> which in it owne nature is doubtfull, or from the <hi>Diuels faith</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iam. 2. 19.</note> which trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth, becauſe it doth not apply. 3. That the <hi>Godly</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 27. 13. &amp; 77. 9. 10. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke 9. 24. 2. Cor. 12. 7. 8. 9</note> haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as much. 4. What power <note n="r" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. 5. 5. 6. 7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Faith</hi> is of to preſerue true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers from deſpaire, their great feares notwithſtanding. And 5. That it is therefore <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 8. 15. 16. 26. 27. Matth. 14. 30. 31.</note> like vnto the <hi>Spirit of Prayer,</hi> which the faithfull diſtreſſed feele weake in themſelues, but find ſtrong in the effect.</p>
            <p>Q. How may we know when we haue a true faith?</p>
            <p>A. When wee know that our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15261:9"/> faith <hi rend="sup">t</hi> is grounded on <hi>Gods Word;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 14. 17.</note> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Philip. 4. 4. 5. 1. Pet. 1. 6. 8.</note> Reioyceth in the Lord more or leſſe; but alwaies vnſeignedly, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding croſſes and tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 7. 18. 20. Galat. 5. 6. Iam. 2. 18.</note> In loue bringeth forth good fruits, which are good workes.</p>
            <p>Q. What calleſt thou good workes?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 19. 16. 17.</note> Thoſe which God requireth in the ten Commandements.</p>
            <p>Q. What if good workes be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="z" place="margin">Iam. 2. 20. 21. 26. Titus 1. 16.</note> Then is inſtifying faith wanting whatſoeuer we profeſſe.</p>
            <p>Q. Can good workes iuſtifie?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 29. Iam. 2. 18.</note> They iuſtifie in declaring vs to be iuſt before men, <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 3. 27. 28. &amp; 4. 2. 5. 6</note> but they do not iuſtifie in making vs iuſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p>Q. Why ſo?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 3. 10. &amp; 5. 3. 4. 17. Hebr. 12. 13.</note> Becauſe they are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly done of vs.</p>
            <p>Q. To what purpoſe ſerue they then?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 5. 16.</note> To glorifie. God, <note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. 2. 12.</hi>
               </note> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit our brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Touching our ſelues what vſe haue they?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15261:9"/>
            <p>A. <note n="f" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim. 1. 5. Iam. 2. 22.</hi>
               </note> They are certaine ſignes of vnfained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 2. 6. 7.</note> and of GOD are well rewarded.</p>
            <p>Q. If good workes be rewarded, then they merite, if they merite, then they iuſtifie?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8. 17. 18</note> They are rewarded for Chriſt his ſake, <note n="i" place="margin">Hebr. 10. 36. 2. Cor. 1. 20.</note> and becauſe of Gods promiſe, <note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 17. 7. 8. &amp;c.</note> but not for their owne worthines</p>
            <p>Q. How are <hi>Faith</hi> &amp; good works begun in vs?</p>
            <p>A <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 10. 14. 17.</note> By preaching of Gods word, and working <note n="m" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 12 3 4 2. Cor 4. 13.</hi>
               </note> of his holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Q. How are they increaſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and continued in vs?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="n" place="margin">Eph. 4. 1. &amp;c. 2. Cor. 3. 18.</note> By the ſame meanes, and further by the vſe of the <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 4 11.</note> Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and <note n="p" place="margin">Marke 9. 24.</note> prayer.</p>
            <p>Q. What are the Sacraments?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 4. 11.</note> Holy ſignes and ſeales of <note n="r" place="margin">Matth. 26. 26. &amp;c. 1. Cor. 12. 13.</note> Ieſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and his benefits.</p>
            <p>Q. How many Sacraments bee there?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="ſ" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 10. 2. 3 &amp; 12. 13.</hi>
               </note> Two: Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Q Why be there two Sacraments and no more?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15261:10"/>
            <p>A. <note n="t" place="margin">Hebr. 9. 15.</note> Becauſe the maker and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of the new <note n="u" place="margin">Rom 11. 27.</note> Couenant <note n="x" place="margin">Matth. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. 1 Cor. 11. 23. 25</note> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained theſe and no more, <note n="y" place="margin">Marke 1. 4.</note> as ſeales of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Q. What difference is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe two?</p>
            <p>A. Baptiſme ſignifieth our new <note n="z" place="margin">Titus 3. 5.</note> birth, or entring <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 12. 13.</hi>
               </note> into the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant: and therefore we are but once baptiſed.</p>
            <p>Q. How doth the <hi>Supper</hi> of the Lord otherwiſe ſignifie?</p>
            <p>A. Our ſpirituall féeding or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in the Couenant, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 2. 42. 46. &amp; 20. 7. 1. Cor. 11. 24. 26</note> we receiue often, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly once at Eaſter, which is <note n="c" place="margin">Leuit. 23. 6.</note> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh.</p>
            <p>Q. Why are children baptized?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="d" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 7. 14.</hi>
               </note> Becauſe they be the ſéed of the faithfull, and therefore <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 17. 7.</note> within the viſible Couenant, ſo that the ſeale thereof is to be <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 10. 44. 47. Gen. 17. 11. 12.</note> adminiſtred vnto them.</p>
            <p>Q. Why receiue they not the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> of the Lord?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 11. 28.</hi>
               </note> Becauſe they cannot exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine themſelues.</p>
            <p>Q. Of how many things doth a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15261:10"/> Sacrament conſiſt?</p>
            <p>A. Two: a ſigne perceiued <note n="h" place="margin">Mark. 1. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Cor. 11. 23. &amp; 10. 25. 2. 3. 4</note> by ſenſe, and a thing ſignified, not at all perceiued by ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Q. In Baptiſme which is the ſigne, which is the thing ſignified?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 8. 36.</note> Water the ſigne: Chriſt his blood <note n="k" place="margin">Eph. 5. 25. 26. Hebr. 9. 14.</note> the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p>Q. Whath doth the waſhing of the body ſignifie and ſeale vnto vs?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 22. 16. Rom. 5. 9. &amp; 3. 24. 25.</note> The waſhing away of our ſinnes by the blood of <hi>Christ,</hi> which is our <hi>Iustification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What doth it elſe ſignifie and ſeale vnto vs?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 6. 3. 5. 1. Cor. 6. 11.</note> The reforming of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and affections in the name of <hi>Christ,</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Gal. 3. 27. 24. Epheſ. 4. 23.</note> which is our <hi>Sanctification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. In the <hi>Supper</hi> of the Lord, which is the ſigne, which the thing ſignified?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="o" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 11. 23. 24. 25.</hi>
               </note> Bread and wine the ſigne, Chriſt his body and blood the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What ſignifieth the breaking of the bread, and powring of the wine?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="p" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 11. 24.</hi>
               </note> The breaking of his body
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15261:11"/> and <note n="q" place="margin">Marke 14. 24</note> ſhedding of his blood.</p>
            <p>Q. What doth the eating and drinking ſignifie and ſeale vnto vs?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 104. 15.</note> That as bread and wine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth our naturall life: ſo <note n="ſ" place="margin">Iohn 6. 54.</note> Chriſt his body and blood is our ſpirituall food vnto eternall life.</p>
            <p>Q. How ſo?</p>
            <p>A. Becauſe <hi>Christ</hi> is our conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall <note n="t" place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn 1. 7. 9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iustification</hi> and <note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 8. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Why calleſt thou the body and blood of Chriſt ſpirituall food?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="x" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 10. 3. 4. Ioh. 6. 35. 63. Epheſ. 3. 17.</hi>
               </note> Becauſe it is ſpiritually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by faith, not corporally eaten with teeth.</p>
            <p>Q. Are not the body and blood of Chriſt called ſpirituall food, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſubſtance of bread &amp; wine is tranſubſtantiated into the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt his very body and blood, though only the accidents of bread and wine remaine and be ſeene?</p>
            <p>A. No: For ſuch a <hi>Tranſubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> is moſt contrary to this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall banquet, for thrée reaſons.</p>
            <p>Q. Which be they?</p>
            <p>A. If there be ſuch a <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15261:11"/> then this Sacrament ſhould want the outward ſigne. For the accidents; without the ſubſtance of bread and wine cannot nouriſh, and therefore there is no ſigne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by ſenſe, to ſignifie ſpirituall feeding, not perceiued by ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Q. What is your ſecond reaſon?</p>
            <p>A. This <hi>Trauſubstantiation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a miracle, ſhould bee euidently ſéene (as was <note n="y" place="margin">Joh. 2. 8. 9. 10. 11.</note> the tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of water into wine at the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in <hi>Cana</hi>) for confirmation of the word, eſpecially in a Sacrament. Seeing both <note n="z" place="margin">Marke 16. 20</note> miracles, and <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 4. 11.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments be called <hi>Signes,</hi> in regard of ſuch confirmation.</p>
            <p>Q. What is your third reaſon?</p>
            <p>A. By ſuch <hi>Tranſubstantiation,</hi> the ſuppoſed ſpirituall food, ſhould be a body and blood preſently made of bread and wine, and not the body and blood of Chriſt crucified, and long ſince <note n="b" place="margin">Galat. 4. 4.</note> made of a woman, which this ſpirituall banquet doth ſignifie, and ſeale vnto faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers.</p>
            <p>Q. If there be no ſuch <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15261:12"/> how then can wee eate <hi>Christ</hi> his very body, and drinke his very blood, which are bodily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 3. 21.</note> abiding in heauen, and that only by faith ſpiritually?</p>
            <p>A. As they who acknowledge his Maieſtie to bee their only ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and do accordingly ſubmit themſelues vnto his gouernment, become members of the ſame poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique body, whereof his very perſon is head: So they <note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 1. 12. &amp; 6. 35. 37. Act. 4. 12. Epheſ. 4. 13. 15.</note> who by faith pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt to be their only Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and do accordingly committe themſelues to his ſaluation, become members of the ſame myſticall body whereof his very perſon is the head.</p>
            <p>Q. You ſpeake now of the whole perſon, &amp; incorporation; but before of the body and blood of Chriſt, and feeding.</p>
            <p>A. As <note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 12. 13. Epheſ. 5. 23. Ioh. 15. 1. 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Incorporation,</hi> and other borrowed ſpeeches of <hi>Holy writ,</hi> ſo <note n="f" place="margin">&amp; 6. 56. 1. <hi>Cor. 10. 16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Feeding</hi> ſignifieth our ſpirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, yet with ſome further conſideration.</p>
            <p>Q. What is that?</p>
            <p>A. To teach vs that we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15261:12"/> into <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 12. 32. 33 Rom. 6. 3.</note> Chriſt crucified. As wee are fedde with the fleſh of beaſts not liuing, <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 10 13.</note> but ſlaine.</p>
            <p>Q. Is not this the reaſon why both bread and wine be neceſſarily diſtributed in the Lords Supper?</p>
            <p>A. Yes: and further, <note n="i" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. 24. 25. Matth 19 6.</hi>
               </note> becauſe of the inſtitution: <note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 11. 26.</hi>
               </note> for a liuely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of Chriſt his death: <note n="l" place="margin">Joh. 19. 32. 33. 34.</note> differing from the thieues death: <note n="m" place="margin">Leuit. 7. 2.</note> and anſwering to the ſacrifices: <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 104. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh 6. 35. 54. 55.</note> and for the comfortable aſſurance of our perfect nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>Q. Is not then our perfect nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment another conſideration of our ſpirituall feeding, beſides our incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration into Chriſt?</p>
            <p>A. Yes: for <note n="o" place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6. 57.</note> if we eate Chriſt, we ſhall liue by Chriſt, and <note n="p" place="margin">&amp; 4. 49. 51. 52.</note> that (as it were) with health, <note n="q" place="margin">&amp; 15. 4. 5.</note> which is the effect of ſuch incorporation.</p>
            <p>Q Expreſſe this yet more fully.</p>
            <p>A. As he who corporally feedeth with good digeſtion, feeleth his heart <note n="r" place="margin">Act. 14. 17. 1. King. 19. 7. 8</note> gladded, and the whole man better inabled to performe the actions of naturall life: So be who ſpiritually féedeth by a true faith, feeleth <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 5. 1. 2.</note> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15261:13"/> peace of conſciente, and <note n="t" place="margin">Galat. 2. 20. John 6. 57.</note> the whole man better inabled to performe the actions of a ſpirituall life.</p>
            <p>Q. Then I perceiue that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vſeth borrowed ſpeeches in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard only of <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> and not of <hi>Christ</hi> his body &amp; blood; becauſe our communion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and verily with <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe crucified, is yet by the ſpirituall meane of a true faith.</p>
            <p>A. It is ſo; As may be euidently ſéne in the 6. chapter of <hi>Iohn</hi> ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten quoted. For whereas in the 54. verſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſoeuer eaſeth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood hath eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life;</hi> in the 35 verſe he ſaith, <hi>He that commeth to me ſhall not hunger, and he that beleeueth in me ſhall neuer thirst.</hi> So that <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Comming,</hi> and <hi>Beleeuing</hi> are manifeſtly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> caſe, all on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, And conſequently our recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of <hi>Christ</hi> crucified muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be ſpirituall. As it further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the 12. verſe of the firſt chapter of the ſame booke.</p>
            <p>Q. All that come to the Lords table, do they ſpiritually receiue the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15261:13"/> body and blood of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>A. No: The wicked receiue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uke</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 26. 27. &amp; 22. 14.</note> the ſignes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to their damnation, not <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 13. 2. &amp; 6. 35.</note> the things ſignified to their ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Q. Why ſo?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ 3. 2.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note n="y" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t 8. 11. 12. 1 Cor. 11. 27.</note> Becauſe they receiue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily.</p>
            <p>Q. How may we receiue worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie?</p>
            <p>A. By comming to the Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with <note n="z" place="margin">Iohn 6. 35.</note> Faith and <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 30. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Repentance.</p>
            <p>Q. What is repentance?</p>
            <p>A. A forſaking <note n="b" place="margin">Ezec. 33. 11.</note> of our ſinnes and turning <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</note> to God, by <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 4. 17.</note> amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life.</p>
            <p>Q. Can we beleeue and repent of our ſelues?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="e" place="margin">Philip. 1. 29. Ezec. 11. 19.</note> No: And therfore we muſt craue <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke 9. 24. Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em.</hi> 31. 18.</note> theſe and all other graces of God by hartie prayer.</p>
            <p>Q. What is prayer?</p>
            <p>A. <note n="g" place="margin">Luke 18. 1. &amp;c.</note> An earneſt requeſt to God, in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> name <note n="h" place="margin">Iohn 14. 13.</note> of Chriſt for all things <note n="i" place="margin">Iam. 4. 3.</note> neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Q. How may we be ſure to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all things neceſſary?</p>
            <p>A <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22. 33</note> If we aſke in faith: <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> For
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15261:14"/> ſo God hath promiſed. To whom b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glory for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A PRAYER.</head>
            <p>O Moſt mercifull and gracious Father, whereas we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of our ſelues to perceiue the things of the Spirit, <note n="m" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 2. 14.</hi>
               </note> being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men, yea ſo fooliſh <note n="n" place="margin">Ierem. 4. 22.</note> and of no vnderſtanding, that howſoeuer, we are wiſe to do euill, to do well we haue no knowledge, we moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee for Chriſt his ſake to remember thy <note n="o" place="margin">Ier. 31. 33.</note> Couenant, and teach vs by thy <note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 16. 13.</note> holy Spirit, which ſearcheth all things, <note n="q" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 2. 10. 12.</hi>
               </note> yea the deepe things of God, to know thoſe things which thou haſt giuen vs. Suffer vs not therefore, O Lord, with the <note n="r" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh. 5. 19. 20.</hi>
               </note> world to lie in wickednes, but giue vs a mind to know thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, who is very God and eternall life. And open our <note n="ſ" place="margin">Luke 24. 45.</note> vnderſtanding, that we <note n="t" place="margin">Iohn 5. 39.</note> ſearching may vnderſtand the Scriptures, which are able to <note n="u" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim. 3. 14. 15.</hi>
               </note> make vs wiſe vnto ſaluation. And
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15261:14"/> whereas ſinne <note n="x" place="margin">Hebr. 12. 1. 2</note> hangeth ſo faſt on, that we cannot run the race that is ſet before vs, with an eye ſtill looking to Ieſus the Author and finiſher of our faith, with groning ſpirits we intreate thee, to ſeparate them from vs, as far as the Eaſt is <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 103. 12.</note> from the Weſt, that hauing laid a ſure foundation <note n="z" place="margin">Hebr. 6. 1.</note> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead works and faith towards God, we may be led forward to perfection, and hauing learned the doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt, we may grow <note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 4. 15. 13</note> vp into him which is our head, vntill we meete together in the vnitie of faith, and knowledge of the Son of God vnto a perfect man, and vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulnes of Chriſt. That ſo growing in <note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Pet. 3. 17. 18</hi>
               </note> grace and knowledge of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, we be not plucked away with the error of the wicked, and fall from our owne ſtedfaſtnes: but hauing the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16. 17.</note> of God reuealed to vs from faith to faith, we may perceiue indeed, the Goſpel to be to vs the power of God to ſaluation, and ſo go from ſtrength<note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 7.</note> to ſtrength, till we appeare before
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15261:15"/> God in Zion. Which graces, with all other bleſſings ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, for our ſelues and euery member of thy Church, we beg of thee O holy Father in the name and mediation of our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, further recommending our ſelues, our prayers and wants to thy fatherly conſideration, concluding in that moſt holy prayer which our Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter himſelfe hath taught vs, ſaying: <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15261:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
